<div>
	<div class="session_title">Practical T/BDD - Half Day Hands-on Lab (morning, repeats afternoon)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
			<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>.NET</div>
			<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>100/200</div>
			<div><b>Abstract: </b>Seen enough "Hello World" presentations on Behavior/Test Driven Design?  Enough already!  In this hands-on lab, we are going to develop an application given a set of specifications.  We will be covering all of the usual suspects including pair programming, testing frameworks, and mocking. So come with a laptop (or a partner with a laptop), and get ready to code!  (We will find you a partner if you don't have one or a laptop, so don't let that stop you!) This session is a half-day session and repeats in the afternoon.</div>
			<div>Presented By: <b>Phil Japikse</b></div>
			<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Phil is a Microsoft MVP and holds MCSD, MCDBA, CSM, and CSP certifications with experience that includes Smart Client/WPF, ASP.NET/MVC, eCommerce, and mentoring teams in .Net, SQL Server, and Agile.  Phil is a contributing author to www.nPlus1.org, teaches custom classes,  a national speaker, and a passionate member of the developer community (serving as a director for the Cincy .Net User’s Group).  Phil works as a Principal Consultant with Pinnacle Solutions Group, Inc. (www.pinnsg.com), and also serves as a Firefighter/Paramedic. You can follow Phil on twitter via www.twitter.com/skimedic and read his blog at www.skimedic.com/blog.	</div>
		</div>
	<div class="session_title">Test Driven Development: From Concept to Deployment with Leon Gersing (all day)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
			<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Ruby</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200</div>
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>
		Objective: Learn Test Driven Development by creating a public-facing website in an all day, hands-on workshop.
		Test Driven Development's benefits are often realized over time on real projects. One hour sessions or short workshops nearly always lack the context of TDD's fit and benefits in a real project. TDD isn't so much about testing as it is about using the process to evolve a solution's design as you solve your business problems.
		This all-day workshop will have participants walk through an entire project from start to finish, deploying a finished, working application to the Heroku hosting service at the end of the day. Participants will use tools focusing on patterns and practices popular in the software craftsmanship movement; combining them with Agile practices in a low stress, mentoring environment.
		The project will be a feedback application for conferences where attendees can evaluate speakers, venue, costs, rate events and recommend them to friends. Some of the tools participants will use include:
		<ul>
		<li>Cucumber for higher-level specifications</li>
		<li>RSpec for domain specifications</li>
		<li>Ruby on Rails</li>
		
		<li>JQuery and QUnit</li>
		<li>Git for version control, hosted in Github for the broader CodeMash public to review</li>
		<li>Heroku for cloud hosting</li>
		</ul>

		Workshop participants will also learn Agile processes:
		<ul>
		<li>A Kanban board to manage a pull-based backlog of work items</li>
		<li>Standup meetings to facilitate communication</li>
		<li>Pair programming</li>
		<li>End-of-day retrospective</li>
		
		</ul>
		
		At the end of the day, participants will have created an entire application from top to bottom and deployed it to the wild. Participants will have learned a number of highly valuable skills and tools in a real world context, enabling them to more effectively apply that knowledge to their own environments.
		
		</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: Leon Gersing<b></b></div>
		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>

Leon has been bringing value to clients large and small for over ten years, and has a passion for technology, art and community. He has experience using technologies ranging from ASP.Net and C++, to Objective-C, Ajax, and Actionscript – and of course, Ruby and Rails. Leon also has high hopes for IronRuby and the much needed efficiency and agility that it has the potential to bring to the .Net world.

A believer in building strong communities, Leon spends time presenting on a wide variety of development topics at events and user groups in the region. He loves nothing more than to be around other developers, working together to create something unique and fresh; something that has never been done before. He believes there is no challenge that can't be overcome with passion and creativity. He spends his spare time with his wife, two beautiful girls, two sweet kitties, and his ukulele.
</div>
		
		
	</div>
		
		
		<a name="Ruby"></a>		
		<div class="session_title">Ruby Fundamentals with Joe O'Brien and Jim Weirich (half-day, morning only)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Ruby</div>

		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>100/200</div>
		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>		</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Joe O'Brien and Jim Weirich</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speakers: </b>
Joe is a father, speaker, author and developer. Before helping found EdgeCase, LLC, Joe was a developer with ThoughtWorks and spent much of his time working with large J2EE and .NET systems for Fortune 500 companies. He has spent his career as a developer, project manager, and everything in between. Joe is a passionate member of the open source community. He co-founded the Columbus Ruby Brigade and helped organize the Chicago Area Ruby Users Group. His passions are Agile Development in the Enterprise, Ruby, and demonstrating to the Fortune 500 the elegance and power of this incredible language.
		
Jim Weirich has been active in the software development world for over twenty-five years, with experience that ranges from real-time data acquisition for jet engine testing to image processing and web services for the financial industry. Although Jim has experience in C++ and Java/J2EE technologies, his real passion is about delivering business value in a timely and efficient manner, and one of the best ways of doing just that is leveraging the power of Ruby and Rails. Jim is very active in the Ruby community and has contributed to several Ruby projects, including the Rake build system and the RubyGems package software.

		</div>
		
		
	</div>

		

		<a name="Patterns"></a>

		<div class="session_title">Advanced Presentation Patterns with Jeremy D. Miller (half day, afternoon)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Mixed</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200/300</div>
		

		<div><b>Abstract: </b> This advanced talk covers concerns for creating testable, maintainable presentation logic for your applications. Attendees will learn about different forms of separated presentation approaches, such as the Passive View, Supervising Controller, Presentation Model (MVVM), and Model 2 type MVC architectures with a focus on when they're applicable. Attendees will also discuss how the "Model" portion of these architectures fits in to place, as well as inter-component communication approaches. You'll also discover different approachs for constructing your software, such as Presenter First versus Presenter/View.

		Finally, you'll learn about coordinating screens and services with the Event Aggregator pattern, some homegrown patterns for screen activation lifecycle, and using an IoC tool to make a very extensible application architecture.</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Jeremy D. Miller</b></div>
		

		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b></div>
		

		
	</div>

	<a name="NETBasics"></a>
		<div class="session_title">.NET Basics with Keith Elder (all day)</div>

		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>.NET</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>100/200</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>This all-day session is targeted to anyone new to .NET. You'll start out with basic "What is .NET?" and move through building applications on in various .NET technologies.  Topics covered include:
		<ul>

		<li><b>What is .NET?</b> Discusses the fundamentals of the .NET platform, what it is, where it can be used, and a few myths about .NET.</li>
		<li><b>How to Use Your Hammer - Visual Studio</b> Walks you through how to use Visual Studio features like Intellisense, Source Control integration, debugging, and other critical foundational skills.</li>
		<li><b>A Programmer's Primer Programming in C#</b> Covers the basics of the C# language from Object Oriented Programming principles all the way to generics, collections, and LINQ. This is a programmer’s primer, which means you should already know at least one language and have some experience programming.</li>
		<li><b>Client Applications </b> Covers standard Windows applications, Windows mobile applications and newer Windows applications based on Windows Presentation Foundation (WPF).</li>

		<li><b>Web Applications</b>Covers the variety of ways to build web-based applications in .NET. standard ASP.NET, ASP.NET MVC, Silverlight and Web Services.</li>
		</ul>
		</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Keith Elder</b></div>

		

		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Keith Elder is the co-host of the popular online technology podcast Deep Fried Bytes. He is also a Team Leader / Sr. Software Engineer for Quicken Loans, the nation's largest online mortgage lender based in Livonia, MI and is the founder of the Hattiesburg, MS .Net User Group called Hub City NUG. Keith is an experienced technologist, systems administrator, software engineer, speaker, trainer and all around geek. 

As an experienced educator, trainer and speaker he has logged thousands of hours in front of the classroom teaching students of varying ages from the 6th grade to the college level. He has trained countless developers from various business sectors ranging from top auto manufactures, fortune 500 companies and Universities. 

As a Microsoft MVP and INETA speaker he speaks throughout the United States at major technical conferences, Code Camps, and .Net User Groups. Keith's ability to explain complex topics with a friendly common sense southern attitude make him a highly regarded speaker at technical conferences. You can read more about Keith's interests, hobbies, rants and raves on his blog at http://keithelder.net/blog/.
</div>
		
		
	</div>

		
		
		<a name="BootBiz"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Bootstrapping your business with Nate Kohari and James Avery(half-day, morning)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>N/A</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>N/A</div>
		

		<div><b>Abstract: </b>In this pre-compiler session Nate Kohari and James Avery will discuss how to start a technology business without venture capital funding. They will draw on their Experiences building and launching AgileZen (http://agilezen.com) and building Adzerk (http://adzerk.com) and Zerk Media (http://zerkmedia.com).

In the first half James and Nate will relate stories of building their businesses, what issues they ran into, and how things turned out. Nate and James will also look to the audience to share their startup experiences, whether they are running a successful business or just getting started.

James and Nate will then get into the details of starting your own business. They will cover how to select a good idea and what ideas and business models work best for a bootstrapping startup. They will talk about how to find the time to build that product or service (and cover the financial costs involved). They will offer advice on what technologies and techniques to use and what to avoid. Finally, they will cover how to market that startup on a shoestring budget and get the customers that will pay your bills.
</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Nate Kohari and James Avery</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speakers: </b>James Avery is a founder and president of Zerk Media LLC, which runs The Lounge and Ruby Row advertising networks. James is also the founder and owner of Infozerk Inc. which provides .NET and Ruby consulting. James has been working with .NET since 2001 and has been a web developer since 1996. He has written books for Microsoft Press, Wrox, and O'Reilly Press. James has written articles for MSDN Magazine and Dr. Dobbs.
		Nate Kohari is co-founder and CTO of Enkari, Ltd., makers of Zen, a web-based project management system which applies ideas from lean manufacturing to project management. Nate has been working with the web since 1996, and .NET since 2004. In addition to entrepreneurship, Nate is also committed to open-source software, and is the author of Ninject, the popular open-source dependency injection framework.
		</div>
		
		
	</div>

		
		
		<a name="Author"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Getting Published in an Evolving Industry: How to Survive and Even Thrive with Jason Gilmore, Michael Kimsal, and James Avery (half-day, afternoon)</div>

		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>N/A</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>100</div>
		

		<div><b>Abstract: </b>To paraphrase Mark Twain, "The reports of publishing's demise are greatly exaggerated." Despite the considerable pall seemingly draping the publishing industry these days, what we're actually witnessing is one of the most exciting transformations since the printing press. If you've ever had an interest in publishing your IT knowledge, join Jason Gilmore, Michael Kimsal, and James Avery for a look into three key facets of the IT publishing industry, including book publishing, electronic magazine publishing, and online advertising.

Jason Gilmore will kick things off with an introduction to the traditional and independent (self) publishing industries, explaining the process involved in taking a book from concept to completion in both instances. You'll learn all about the nuances of working with a traditional publisher, including contractual matters, how royalties actually work, and in what ways you can realistically expect to profit from writing a book. Jason will also discuss his experience (both positive and negative) authoring, producing, publishing, and marketing the popular book "Easy PHP Websites with the Zend Framework", sharing insight the Amazon Advantage sales channel, shipping logistics, and whether readers actually care about a polished work.

Michael Kimsal is next to take the stage, discussing his experiences founding and growing the electronic magazines GroovyMag and JSMag in an environment considered to be the worst in the history of magazine publishing.

James Avery will conclude the seminar with a look at how online advertising is offering publishers of all sizes with an alternative revenue model, sharing his knowledge and experienced gained founding and operating The Lounge and Ruby Row advertising networks.</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Jason Gilmore, Michael Kimsal, James Avery</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speakers: </b>W. Jason Gilmore is founder of W.J. Gilmore, LLC, a publishing and consulting firm based out of Columbus, Ohio which runs the niche publisher EasyPHPWebsites.com. In his previous role as Apress' open source editorial director, Jason led the development of more than 60 books, transforming Apress' open source line from near obscurity to one of the industry's most respected programs. He is the author of five books, including the bestselling "Beginning PHP and MySQL: From Novice to Professional" (currently in its third edition), and the recently published "Easy PHP Websites with the Zend Framework". He has more than 100 articles within popular publications such as Linux Magazine, and is a regular contributor to Developer.com. Jason is a CodeMash (http://www.codemash.org) cofounder and speaker chair, a nonprofit organization tasked with hosting an annual namesake developer's conference, and was a member of the 2008 MySQL Conference speaker selection board.

Michael Kimsal is the publisher of GroovyMag and JSMag, as well as a web developer, trainer and author. Over the years, he's made livings working with PHP, ASP, Perl and too many other technologies to mention. He runs the WebDevRadio podcast, and currently lives outside Raleigh, NC with his wife and three cats.

James Avery is a founder and president of Infozerk LLC, which runs The Lounge and Ruby Row advertising networks. James is also the founder and owner of Infozerk Inc. which provides .NET and Ruby consulting.
James has been working with .NET since 2001 and has been a web developer since 1996. He has written books for Microsoft Press, Wrox, and O'Reilly Press. James has written articles for MSDN Magazine and Dr. Dobbs.</div>
		
		

	</div>
		
		<a name="Coaching"></a>

		<div class="session_title">End-to-End Coaching with Dave Laribee and Steve Harman (half-day, morning)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>N/A</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>Coming together as a product development team requires coaching all the way around. Join Steve and Dave in sharing a collection of coaching techniques, experiences and exercises aimed at transforming workgroups to real, collaborative collectives.

 
Topics covered include:
<ul>
<li>Rolling wave planning: from product analysis to design to implementation</li>
<li>Features, Stories, Slices, and Tests</li>
<li>Value stream mapping and Kanban</li>
<li>Emergent design, collective ownership</li>

<li>Language-oriented programming and testing</li>
<li>Tackling technical debt and improvement opportunities</li>
<li>Systemic Domain-Driven Design: how DDD fits into an Agile/Pull-System workflow</li>
<li>Looking to the near future, AKA stuff we're gonna try</li>
</ul>
		</div>

		

		<div>Presented By: <b>David Laribee and Steve Harman</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speakers: </b></div>
		
		
	</div>
		
		
		
		<a name="Competency"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Competency and Leadership in Software Development (half-day, afternoon)</div>

		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>N/A</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>N/A</div>
		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>Expert performance can be found in many fields – from music to athletics, from science to engineering –and yes, even in software development.  We know that there is a great deal of difference between elite performers and entry level practitioners, but do we know where expertise comes from and how to develop it?  This session will discuss the latest research on expertise and the implications for software development.

Next we move beyond individual expertise to consider high performing teams and top notch companies, especially those that have sustained their dominance over time.  The session will present a way to think about leadership roles with an emphasis on technical competency and superior customer outcomes.

</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Mary Poppendieck</b></div>
		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b></div>
		
		

	</div>

		

		<a name="OOP"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Software Engineering Fundamentals Workshop: OOP, SOLID, and More (half-day, morning)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>.NET, Java, Ruby</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200</div>

		

		<div><b>Abstract: </b>We all know that software development is hard, but learning how to design good object-oriented solutions can decrease the friction in software development, reduce bugs, and make your code easier to change.  First, we'll go over principles of object oriented programming, the "SOLID" software design principles, separation of concerns, a brief overview of dependency injection frameworks, and more object-oriented tips and tricks that will help you write better, cleaner, more flexible code.  Then you get to whip out your laptop, pair up with a friend, and put your newly discovered chops to work by refactoring some very un-solid code into a more object-oriented solution that will be more flexible, readable, testable, and a pleasure to work with.  We will have code samples in Java, .NET, and Ruby on Rails and experts in all three languages who can help you out.

Requirements: If you want to do the code samples, you will need a laptop with a development environment for the language of your choice (Java, .NET, Ruby).  If you don't have a laptop, come anyway and pair up with someone who does.
</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Jon Kruger</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Jon Kruger is a Project Engineer and Mentor with Quick Solutions in Columbus, OH where he provides technical leadership for .NET development projects.  Jon has over 8 years experience in various different programming languages (mostly C#/.NET) and is always looking for ways to create better quality software and speed up the software development process.  You can follow Jon on his blog (jonkruger.com) or on Twitter (twitter.com/jonkruger). </div>

		
		
	</div>
		
		<a name="Craftsmanship"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Software Craftsmanship (half-day, afternoon)</div>

		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>.NET, Java, Ruby</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200/300</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>Join your peers and fellow craftsmen in a variety of coding kata and exercises designed to improve your skills as software developers.  Led by organizers of the Hudson Software Craftsmanship group, this interactive session will help you sharpen your tools and learn from others.  Experienced developers from all backgrounds are welcome, as are beginners.  Attendees should already be comfortable with a programming language of their choice and if possible should bring along a laptop computer with their development tools installed, including a unit test tool.</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Steve Smith and Brendan Enrick</b></div>
		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Steve is a Senior Architect with The Code Project, a Microsoft Regional Director, and a Microsoft MVP.  He has been writing software professionally since 1997 and is one of the founders and organizers of the Hudson Software Craftsmanship group, which meets monthly in Hudson, Ohio.  Steve is also a co-founder of NimblePros, an agile software consulting company located in Hudson, and Lake Quincy Media (now a part of The Code Project), which manages the largest advertising network dedicated to Microsoft developers. 

Steve lives in Kent, Ohio with his wife Michelle and their two children.  You can find him online at  http://SteveSmithBlog.com and on twitter at http://twitter.com/ardalis. 
Brendan is a Lead Developer with NimblePros, an agile software consulting company located in Hudson, Ohio. Brendan is a Microsoft MVP whose expertise is in ASP.NET, and he is one of the founders and organizers of the Hudson Software Crafstmanship group, which meets monthly in Hudson, Ohio. He blogs at http://Brendan.Enrick.com/ and can be found on Twitter under the alias @brendoneus.

</div>

		
		
	</div>
		
		<a name="Mac"></a>
		<div class="session_title">A Taste of Cocoa (half-day, morning)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Mac/Cocoa</div>

		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200/300</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>When was the last time you smiled while developing? The same folks who brought you Snow Leopard and the iPhone also give you the tools for developing for those platforms. "Give you" as in "they're free". Sure, you can insert your "it's not open" rant here or you can come learn what a pleasure it is to develop for Mac OS X in a C-based dynamic language using Interface Builder, Xcode, and Instruments.

You will build a series of projects during this Pre-Compiler session that are designed to introduce you to the tools and techniques for coding Cocoa applications for Snow Leopard. You'll develop a GUI using Interface Builder and learn to write controllers in Xcode and connect the two together. You'll create your own simple models in code and then see how to create more flexible ones using Core Data. This isn't a tour through the APIs---it's an exploration of different ways of sending messages between objects using Objective-C and Cocoa.

You will need an Intel-based Mac running Snow Leopard along with the latest version of the developer tools. The developer tools are included with your installation disks but are not installed by default.
</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Daniel Steinberg</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Daniel H Steinberg's most recent book is "Cocoa Programming: A Quick Start Guide for Developers" from The Pragmatic Programmers. He has edited many Mac titles for the Prags as well.  He co-teaches the iPhone Studio and the Cocoa Studio for the Pragmatic Studios and has spoken at WWDC, JavaOne, and bunches of other places. Daniel has also produced podcasts for Sun, Apple, Disney, Intel, and many others.</div>
		
		

	</div>
		
		<a name="iPhone"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Introduction to iPhone SDK Development (half-day, afternoon)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">

		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>iPhone</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200/300</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>A new platform, a different language, an unfamiliar IDE... can you learn how to develop for the iPhone and iPod touch?  Of course you can!  In this completely redesigned introductory tutorial, we'll build a set of basic applications. You'll learn how to use the Xcode IDE, the Objective-C language, and the Cocoa Touch frameworks, as we work through the essential concepts of all iPhone applications.  Together, we'll build out examples of the major iPhone UI application metaphors:  
single-view apps, flipping utility apps, navigation apps, and tab- based apps.  We'll also leave lots of time for questions, experimentation, and attendee-chosen topics.

Participants will need an Intel-based Mac with the latest release version of the iPhone SDK already installed (see http://developer.apple.com/iphone/
  for more details).  You do not need to join the paid iPhone developer program to work through the projects in this precompiler.</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Chris Adamson</b></div>
		

		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Chris Adamson is a writer, editor, developer and consultant specializing in media software development. He is the co-author of "iPhone SDK Development" (Pragmatic Progammers), author of “QuickTime for Java: A Developer’s Notebook” (O’Reilly), and co-author of “Swing Hacks” (O’Reilly) and has served as Editor for the developer websites ONJava and java.net. He maintains a corporate identity as Subsequently &amp; Furthermore, Inc. (http://www.subfurther.com/) and writes the [Time code]; blog at http://www.subfurther.com/blog .</div>
		
		
	</div>

		
		<a name="Watir"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Scripting Web Tests with Watir (half-day, morning)</div>

		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Watir/Ruby</div>
		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200</div>
		

		<div><b>Abstract: </b>Automated function testing is a challenging, critical, yet overlooked part of the software development lifecycle. In this hands-on, tutorial led by Charley Baker, a lead developer on the open source Watir testing tool, we'll be writing and running tests that verify page presentation and application behavior and learn some basic Ruby along the way.</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Charley Baker</b></div>
		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b>Charley is a lead developer on Watir, a web testing tool written in Ruby. He has 15 years of experience in the IT field, working as developer, team lead, QA Architect and . He has been working in the software and IT industry for 15 years as a developer, QA Engineer and other roles where necessary.  Charley has worked in startups from small boutiques to large scale as well as enterprise level well established companies, such as Gap Inc direct where he has been serving the role of QA Architect for the past several years. His wide range of experience and interest in technology has afforded him the opportunity to work with C/C++, Java, Php, Perl, Windows API, and his current passion - Ruby. 
As well as Ruby, Charley's current passions are focused on Agile collaboration in a distributed Enterprise environment, open source and delivering high value projects. He lives in Denver and loves spending time with his two boys, wife, and dog when he's not travelling. 
</div>
		

		
	</div>
		
				<a name="OSGi"></a>
		<div class="session_title">Modular Java Using OSGi (half-day, afternoon)</div>
		<div class="sessionItem">
		<div><b>Technology/Platform: </b>Java</div>

		<div><b>Difficulty Level: </b>200/300</div>

		
		<div><b>Abstract: </b>Java is an object-oriented language so naturally it’s modular, right? We program to interfaces, use Spring to resolve dependencies, and package up our classes into cohesive units. Unfortunately we then take a step back and consolidate them into one monolithic WAR file that gets loaded into a single class loader. Even worse, we may try to keep them separated in WAR, EAR, and JAR files but then interconnect these packages via web services, RMI, or some other ceremonial method.

OSGi has garnered a lot of publicity lately because it solves these common problems of “modularizing” Java in a simple and easy to use fashion. We'll break the chains of comfort that many Java devs have built over the last decade by exploring a more modular approach to many everyday problems in Java. This hands on talk will have attendees pair up to build a traditional multi-tiered, enterprise Java application, with the appropriate tools and techniques of OSGi. Testing OSGi based applications, deploying web applications, extending modules using fragments, leveraging enterprise repositories, and correctly decomposing enterprise systems into cohesive, loosely coupled modules will be covered in depth via hands on exploration.

Each pair will require a laptop with a minimum of 
<ul>

<li>Java 1.6</li>
<li>Eclipse Equinox</li>
<li>Pax Construct</li>
<li>Maven</li>
<li>IDE of choice</li>

</ul>
</div>

		
		<div>Presented By: <b>Todd Kaufman</b></div>

		
		<div><b>About the Speaker: </b> Todd Kaufman is a developer, architect, manager, and cheerleader of IT projects large and small. He has over 10 years of experience in software development and has released production software to various clients using Agile, Waterfall, Java, Ruby, .NET, and everything in between. Todd has presented to passionate geeks like himself at a variety of user events and regional conferences, as his huge ego needs to be stoked on a regular basis. Todd is currently feeding his family courtesy of the good people at Pillar Technology.
</div>
		

		
	</div>

         